Guide to the Dwight Sanderson papers, 1894-1960,
Sanderson, Dwight papers, 1894-1960
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Dwight Sanderson papers, 1894-1960, 1894-1943 (bulk)
21-33-73
Dwight (Ezra Dwight), Sanderson 1878-1944.
7.8 cubic ft.
Diaries, bibliographies, manuscripts, student papers, correspondence, publications, a scrapbook, photograph albums, and class materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes 43 annual diaries of appointments; bibliographies; student papers; correspondence; papers on the family, marriage, and other topics; lecture outlines for classes on rural sociology, social psychology, and sociology; publications by Sanderson; scrapbook of articles following his retirement; post retirement letters; a photocopied excerpt from A Brief History of Entomology at the Agricultural and Mechanical College of Texas concerning Sanderson and Glenn W. Herrick (1960); five albums of photographs and postcards from European travels, 1925/1926 and 1935; and other materials pertaining to Sanderson's work in rural sociology and related fields. Also, letter from Pearl Buck, written from Nanking, China, July 6, 1930.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of rural sociology, New York State College of Agriculture at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes 43 annual diaries of appointments; bibliographies; student papers; correspondence; papers on the family, marriage, and other topics; lecture outlines for classes on rural sociology, social psychology, and sociology; publications by Sanderson; scrapbook of articles following his retirement; post retirement letters; a photocopied excerpt from A Brief History of Entomology at the Agricultural and Mechanical College of Texas concerning Sanderson and Glenn W. Herrick (1960); five albums of photographs and postcards from European travels, 1925/1926 and 1935; and other materials pertaining to Sanderson's work in rural sociology and related fields. Also, letter from Pearl Buck, written from Nanking, China, July 6, 1930.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sanderson, Dwight1878-1944.; Buck, Pearl S.(Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Herrick, Glenn W.; Cornell University--Faculty.; New York State College of Agriculture.Dept. of Rural Sociology.
Subjects:
Family.; Sociology.; Sociology, Rural.; Social psychology.; College teachers.; Sociologists.
Places:
Europe--Description and travel.
Form and Genre Terms:
Bibliographies.; Diaries.; Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Four Years of County Planning & Development (mimeographed copy), Sept. 1938 (Box 1)
- A Demonstration in County Development (3 bound copies), 1935 (Box 1)
- Tompkins County Schools (3 folders), 1922-1939 (Box 1)
- The Family (Box 2)
  (All of the following are from Chapters I, VIII, XI, XII, XIII, XIV; Chapters XV, XVI, XVII, XXI were noted in collection as missing)
  - Physiology and Psychology of Petting, Legal Aspects of Betrothal, 1932 (Box 2)
  - The Prediction of Adjustment in Marriage, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Husband-Wife Relations in Marriage, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Family Bibliography, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Extracts from Thomas-Tusser's Book on Huswifery" (edition of 1580)., 1932 (Box 2)
- Federal Extension Service (Boy's and Girl's Club Work), 1918 (Box 2)
- FERA (Federal Emergency Relief Admin. ), 1934 (Box 2)
- Group I & II, 1937-1943 (Box 2)
- Rural Organization 16 Lecture Outlines, Notes, 1918-1921 (Box 3)
- Rural Organization Miscellanea (Box 3)
- Rural Secondary Schools, Social Studies, 1915- (Box 3)
- Rural Sociology I-IV, 1939-1943 (Box 3)
- Social Psychology (Box 3)
- Sociology 15 (Introductory), 1915 (Box 3)
- "State Departments of Agriculture " by Dwight Sanderson. Written at University of Chicago in 1916., 1916 (Box 3)
- Annual Cornell School for Missionaries, 1930-1940 (Box 4)
- "Moral Education in the Public Schools" (Box 4)
- Philosophy 31 (Paper presented at University of Chicago), Dec. 16, 1916 (Box 4)
- Psychology (Abnormal) Paper,, and Sociology Paper prepared by D. Sanders on at University of Chicago, 1915 (Box 4)
- "A Psychological Account of the Program of Religion" - Paper given at University of Chicago, Nov. 2, 1917 (Box 4)
- Rural Community I -VI I I, 1917-1941 (Box 4)
- Rural Community, No. VIII-XI, 1925-1944 (Box 5)
- "Rural Community Organization for Religious Education" -Rural Church Seminar, 1917 (Box 5)
- Problems of Rural Democracy, 1940 (Box 5)
- Rural Organization, No. l-III, 1917-1924 (Box 5)
- Memorandum concerning Proposed objects of the American Farm Bureau Federation (Prepared and circulated privately at the time of the first meeting of the American Farm Bureau Federation in Chicago. ), 1920 (Box 6)
- Rural Organization - IV-IX, 1917-1922 (Box 6)
- Association Press (National Council of the YMCA), 1939-1941 (Box 7)
- County Agents Course, Mainly 1931 (Box 7)
- Depression Problems, I-II (much correspondence in preparation of Sanderson's manuscript on "New Problems of Rural Youth ), 1936-1937 (Box 7)
- The Family. Chapters I through VIII. Chapters 14, 15, 16, 17 & 21 are missing. (Box 7)
- Factual Material for the Discussion of "Trends in American Standards of Living" by L.S. Cottrell, 1937 (Box 7)
- The Group III, 1928-1934 (Box 8)
- Leadership I-IV (Farm Bureau, Scrapbook, Leadership, Letters & Bibliographies, student papers. Includes a mimeo copy of "Rural Leadership" by D. Sanderson, 1917-1941 (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous correspondence re E.D. Sanderson. Also, various awards and articles., 1901-1943 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Pictures (mostly negatives) and Postcards., ca.1925 (Box 10)
- Diaries; correspondence concerning publication of Sanderson's works, such as "The Farmer and his Community," "Elementary Entomology", "Insect Pests of Farm, Garden and Orchard", and job opportunities around the country., 1899-1950 (Box 11)
- All illustrations and photographs used in books by D. Sanderson, n.d. (Box 12)
- Entomological Publications, 1898-1903 (Box 13)
- New Hampshire Entomology, 1904-1914 (Box 13)
- "Report of the West Virginia Agricultural Experiment station", 1913-1914 (Box 13)
- The Rural Community, 1932 (Box 13)
- Rural Sociology and Rural Social Organization, 1942 (Box 13)
- All the above are by D. Sanderson (Box 13)
- Texas Entomology, 1902-1906 (Box 14)
- "Report of the West Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station", 1911-1912 (Box 14)
- "Report of the State Board of Regents, West Virginia", 1911-1912 (Box 14)
- First Biennial Report, State Crop Pest Commission, West Virginia, 1913- (Box 14)
- Report of the New York State Food Supply Commission, 1918 (Box 14)
- The American Journal of Sociology, pp. 117-260, Nov. 1944 (Box 14)
- Rural Sociology, Vol. II, No. 1, Mar. 1946 (Box 14)
- Volume Report: "The Contribution of Extension Methods, and Techniques Toward the Rehabilitation of War Torn Countries", 1945 (Box 14)
- Scrapbook of early works, 1894-1902 (Box 14)
- Scrapbook of early themes and copies of the Hesperian Star from the Agricultural College in Michigan., 1893-1896 (Box 14)
- NYS Food Supply Commission. Preliminary Report of the Census of the Agricultural Resources of New York State. Bulletin No. 2, 1917 (Box 14)
- Bulletin of the NYS Food Supply Commission. Report of the Conference., 1917 (Box 14)
- Articles, letters re retirement, and letters of condolence to the Sanderson Family, including a black binder of newspaper obituaries. Also two reprints: A Biography of Ezra Dwight Sanderson by W.A. Anderson, and a bibliography of Sanderson up to Sept. 25, 1943. (Box 15)
- Brief biographical sketches of Sanderson and Glenn W. Herrick, publ. 1960, 8 pp. photocopy. (Box 15)
- Letter from Pearl S. Buck., July 6, 1930 (Box 15)
- "The Family in the Life of Today", Handbook for leaders of discussion groups., n.d. (Box 16)
- "With Love and Affection, Respectfully Yours, Graduate Students". (A bound collection of laudatory letters from graduate students to D. Sanderson upon his retirement., 1943 (Box 16)
- One bound volume of early work (including high school themes) by D. Sanderson., 1893-1897 (Box 16)
- One scrapbook of school material and grades through college; including various souvenir programs and invitations., 1885-1901 (Box 16)
- One student notebook on Entomology with hand drawn insect examples., 1930-1933 (Box 16)
- One scrapbook of insect photographs and newspaper clippings., ca. 1910 (Box 16)
- One scrapbook of newspaper clippings re: the Tompkins County Development Association., 1934-1935 (Box 16)
- Two folders: Contents of a scrapbook of clippings and printed items., 1903-1907 (Box 16)
- Album containing postcards and photographs, 1925-1926 (Box 17, Volume 1)
  Locations include France and one in Germany, including Amance, Amiens, Avignon, Bar-le-Duc, Bazancourt, Bellefosse, Bormes, Buire-sur-L'Ancre, Chalons-sur-Marne, Chanteheux, Courtisols, Einville, Fouday, Fressin, Le Treport, Giens, Ribaud, Givry-en-Argonne, Hangest-en-Santerre, Hyeres, La Ferte-Chevresis, Laon, Le Havre, Lyon, Metz, Motteville, Nancy, Paris, Reims, Ribemont, Rilly-la-Montagne, Rouen, Rouffach, Salins-des-Pesquiers, Seichamps, Sezanne, Solbach, Strasbourg, Tronville-en-Barrois, Vertus, Vitry-le-Francois, Witry-les-Reims, and Schwarzwald.
- Album containing postcards and photographs, 1925-1926 (Box 17, Volume 2)
  Locations include France, including Aix-en-Provence, Alps, Arles, Auray, Barjoles, Bordeaux, Camaret, Carnac, Chateaulin, Cite de Carcassone, Correns, Crozon, Damazan, Draguignan, Gardanne, Grimaldi, Guillaumes, L’Aveyron, La Feuillee, La Haute-Garrone, La Rochelle, Landivisiau, Marseille, Menton, Merville, Monaco, Monte-Carlo, Montmeyan, Montpellier, Morlaix, Nerac, Nice, Nimes, Puch, Quimper, Quinson, Rennes, Roscoff, Saint-Malo, Saint-Pol-de-Leon, Sanremo, Sospel, Tonneins, Toulouse, Vianne, and Villefranche.
- Album containing postcards and photographs, 1925-1926 (Box 18, Volume 3)
  Locations include France and Italy, including Amboise, Bernay, Blois, Chambord, Chemonceaux, Courtonne-la-Meurdrac, Grand-Champs, La Bretagne, Laval, Le Mans, Lisieux, Loches, Locmariaquer, Marolles, Sologne, Thiberville, Tours, Vannes, and Florence, Genoa, Milan, Rome, and Venice.
- Album containing postcards and photographs, 1925-1926 (Box 18, Volume 4)
  Locations include Switzerland, Germany, the Czech Republic, Poland, Denmark, the Netherlands, Belgium, including Bern, Lucerne, Romanshorn, Zurich, Berlin, Dresden, Leipzig, Munich, Potsdam, Cesky Brod, Olomouc, Warsaw, Liskow, Aaskov, Copenhagen, Frederiksborg, Haraldsborg, Kronborg, Odense, Roskilde, Svogerslev, Vejen, Amsterdam, Groningen, Volendam, Wageningen, Winschoten, Brussels, and Leuven.
- Album containing postcards and photographs, 1925-1926 (Box 19, Volume 5)
  Locations include Belgium, England, Scotland, France, Italy, Germany, and the Netherlands, including Diksmuide, Ypres, Bruges, Brussels, London, Warwik, Oxford, Grasmere, Durham, Lincoln, Ely, Cambridge, Alloway, Trossachs, Glasgow, Edinburgh, Paris, Tours, Rome, Milan, Berlin, and Amsterdam.
- Album containing postcards and photographs, 1935 (Box 20, Volume 6)
  Locations include Italy, Croatia, Serbia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Greece, Bulgaria, Romania, including Trieste, Gradiste, Mraclin, Nova Gradiska, Tomasica, Zagreb, Kovacevac, Orasje, Veria,Lovech, Cismigiu, and Bucharest.
- Album containing postcards and photograph, 1935 (Box 20, Volume 7)
  Locations include Ireland, Scotland, Wales, England, France, Luxembourg, the former Yugoslavia, Monaco, Switzerland, Germany, and Belgium, including Cashel, Connemara, Foxford, Galway, Kilkenny, Killarney, Larne, Limerick, Londonderry, Sligo, Tipperary, Abbottsford, Aberfeldy, Alloway, Dunfermline, Edinburgh, Fortingall, Glen Coe, Inverness, Loch Lomond, Aberystwyth, Carnarvon, Canterbury, Kenilworth, Aubenas, Blois, Briancon, Eze, Nimes, Paris, Puget-Théniers, Rueil-Malmaison, Sion, Versailles, Diekirch, Brig, Gletsch, Lucerne, Bingen, Heidelberg, Herrenalb, Murg, Offenburg, Worms, and Brussels.
- Diplomas from the University of Michigan, BS 1897; Cornell University, BS 1898; University of Chicago, Ph.D 1921; and certificates from Phi Kappa Phi, the Department of State for the 12th Congress of the International Institute of Sociology, Ministry of Agriculture of Belgium, and the Country of Luxembourg, 1898-1935 (Mapcase-folder 1)